And I apologize for my camera. I'm just
going to put it on, but it's just it's
it's it's not the other one's not
working.
>> Gotcha.
Okay.
And
okay, we are should be starting. So
Desba uh the meeting is yours.
Okay. And this means that I can't see
everybody, right? They can only see me,
>> right? Since you're on your phone. Um,
just so everybody is aware, Despa was uh
is just off of is working off of their
phone. Um, and so we'll be announcing
anything as far as uh that goes into the
chat. We'll relay it from the department
standpoint just so everybody is there.
We'll also do that for other people who
may be on their phones and not on a
computer and don't see the um and don't
aren't able to see the chat. And just as
a quick check before we move forward,
can a couple of people who are attendees
raise your hand? I just want to check
and make sure you can hear us. Okay,
perfect. Thank you, Chris. All right.
Oh, and Brett and Kate and Brenda and
James, thank you all very much. You can
put your hands on down. We just wanted
to make sure that everyone could hear us
and we can move forward. So, Desba uh
and for those who don't know me, I'm
Dominic Zerlo. I'm the center director
for uh the medical cannabis and
psilocybin program uh at the Department
of Health. And I'll just turn it on over
to our chair, Desba. Desba, the meeting
is yours.
>> Yeah, it's ASA Desba. Hi. Um, so I just
wanted to kind of quickly thank you for
all um, being here, especially so
quickly after the festivities um, and
uh, just everything that's been going
on. It's I know if any of you have been
uh, at meeting earlier uh, thanks to
your continued um, dedication. So, just
briefly a little bit about um this
particular committee or at least what
I'm hoping to do here. And also um I
have another meeting scheduled for next
Wednesday at night. I believe from 5:30
to 6:30. It's a little shorter just so
it's not interrupting everyone's evening
so much. Um but I also know that some
people might not be able to do meetings
during the day and I just wanted to make
just to do a little safety net catch for
those. So, if you know of anybody who
wanted to come today, you're not able to
attend because of it's so early to the
holidays, um definitely come in. It'll
be the same same kind of format. This is
more of a listening session where I just
want to hear other people's inputs and
what their concerns are, um what
everything is, what what they've been
doing to work towards equity, access,
and in cultural considerations.
Um it seems like it's a very broad and
very ex yeah very broad kind of
category. Um but I feel in part that um
it can have the possibility of being
plugged into these different areas
because of certain um overlaps
and um and that's just kind of where I'm
I'm coming at it from. I have had uh
someone concerned saying that we should
have specifically for Native American
since I am um the indigenous board
member for the advisory group um that
there should be a separate Native
American
um
committee for for that. Um, but I again
I'm open to what everybody has to say
and their uh concerns and suggestions
mainly in part because there's just been
so much work that everyone has done over
the decades essentially and beyond in
this field and um all of that hard work
I really feel has the opportunity to be
moved into what the state is trying to
do as far as governance when it comes to
use of psilocybin
and beyond. Um,
and
whether or not it can be split up or
there's an additional as far as I
believe Dominic, we're the board is
still looking for two more board
members. Is that correct?
>> That is correct.
>> Process. Okay.
>> Yeah. Um, and so if anybody I guess to
reach out into that that area of like
what's because I don't have I don't also
have all the answers. There might be
some other people who have more answers
or better more informed as far as like
uh admin policies and those types of
things. Um, when it comes to how we're
moving forward and we're also just
trying to form uh what we're what we're
doing and how these committees are going
to be structured. um what the primary
process is it's going to be and how it's
going to be then shared with the rest of
the advisory board um when it comes time
I'm going to be touching my phone a lot
cuz I was trying to get my camera set up
and it just didn't work today um
and
um yeah so again I'm just here to listen
to what other people's concerns are um
what feels like needs to be included um
talked about and established. Um that
being said, just as an example, and I'm
just going to throw out a lot of stuff
um from my perspective and for I'm
coming at, you know, there might be
something that maybe I don't personally
agree with per se, but as a committee
that something is agreed upon that is
going to, you know, my job to me in
essence is that I'm moving that forward
and I'm going to be presenting that
along with everybody else. as a
recommendation or as something that
needs to be thought about. Um, my sole
purpose in being a part of the board as
far as I'm concerned is just relaying
that information and helping to kind of
foster more conversation, thorough
looking at what needs to be addressed,
um, and so forth. So, that was the main
purpose of me joining the board. There's
probably several of you that I don't
know who don't know me or know my
background. So, I don't mind um kind of
giving that. I don't know if anybody
really really wants to go into it. Um I
don't want it to be like too much of a
soap box, but I just wanted to have like
an understanding of, you know, I have my
own prejudices. I have my own biases. I
have my own opinions on things, but that
doesn't mean that that's the thing
that's going to happen as far as the
committee. that that's not the agenda.
The agenda is to move what is being
discussed and what's important as a
group forward. Um and those concerns
being relayed and thought about and um
provided to the rest of the state like
this is what we've talked about. This is
what we recommend as a group as a whole.
So even though I'm chairing this, this
is mostly just me um being a facilitator
in that way. Um, and you know, whether
or not some discussions might get, you
know, heated or um, if something I
really want to have everyone be able to
speak freely to the best of their
ability. I know maybe that it might feel
like that's not possible in some ways
sometimes. Um, just as a throwing that
out there, I do have a 13-year-old, so
it's we've had some very heated
discussions between my kid and myself
and my family where, you know, we really
want to foster that that goal of having
a conversation and really being able to
truly understand and listen to each
other. Um,
yeah. So, um maybe a little bit of my
background just for some people who
don't know me um and like what what I'm
about if that is helpful in any way
because I know I just I gave relayed
that a little. I have worked primarily
in the film industry for uh the last
eight years or so since I moved back to
New Mexico. I am from Santa Fe. Um I
grew up in northern New Mexico in the
Espanola area. Um, for those of you who
attended the first meeting, I did give a
brief introduction of myself. Um, and
you know, growing up in that area, there
was not very much opportunity. Um, at
least that I could see for myself. And I
still feel that there's there's still
some of that. Um, you know, growing up
near Chim.io in that in in that area was
just we heard a lot of stories about,
you know, being careful where you play,
playground, a lot of the same kind of
concerns that I'm seeing now here in
Santa Fe. And those kinds of concerns
are related to drug use and opioid use
and a lot of trauma that has affected
our region in our state as especially
Riaribba is the highest um overdose rate
I think in the country. The stories
about us constantly you know in the
media and those things can wear on you
just in the fact that it's true. But the
thing is what I found with learning
about my own um generational trauma. I'm
from a Mexican immigrant family. My mom
moved here in uh when she was seven from
Mexico. My dad is Navajo. And just
learning more about my indigenity. Um I
I I and fostering that through
storytelling really trying to understand
where this is all coming from and also
being exposed to um psilocybin therapy
several years ago um for the first time.
It really did shine a light on what as a
individual but also as a community a
member of the community and the place
where I'm coming from and my own family
and everything else
really just made me understand that this
is something that can be moved forward
but it takes a collective effort. And
when we talk about equity and access and
cultural considerations in that context,
where we come from, the burdens that we
carry from our ancestors and all of the
trauma that they have endured that we're
still holding on to um collectively as a
community that it can weigh that
community down and it's impossible
sometimes to move forward. Um, even in
my own family, I had uh what I call my
baby cousin overdose from fentinol um a
couple years ago. Um, and it was his
third time and it was his last time.
And um you know those types of things
are not easy to process or go through or
realize or admit to that these things
are so close to home
that sometimes we don't want to
talk about it or see that there's a
problem. And sometimes we think that
just by thinking it'll go away, it'll go
away. And that's not the case. Sometimes
we can't just think positively out of
that hit.
And that's why I feel that access to
this medicine
is so vitally important to our people
because it was something that was taken
away from us years ago whether through
government overreach
um saying that they know what's good for
us. Right? This is a little bit kind of
ironic
but I feel that in the same way that we
can take that back. Um, just briefly,
you know, I was uh explaining that again
as a storyteller,
I wrote an episode for Dark Winds. Um,
kind of specifically with that in mind,
there's a Tony Hillerman version of
Native American spiritual spirituality.
There's the Navajo uh spirituality and
cultural uh teachings. And then there's
a Native American church that was
brought in um to the people as far as as
far as religious practices.
And I will say that a lot of my
knowledge is a little limited. So that's
why everyone else in the community comes
in to bring in all of their knowledge
together so we can look at it um more
thoroughly. But you know that trying to
study and understand where the use of
peyote which is not what we're
discussing as far as psilocybin but just
as a as a background you know coming in
and saying that you know we know what's
better for the Navajo nation and of
course there's this also brings in this
other idea of tribal governance and
sovereignty
um you know federal insight saying this
is what we need to have done and then
taking away and then saying the Navajo
Nation can do what they want and then
the Navajo Nation saying that they still
want to do this and you know now it's so
several years of back and forth back and
forth of saying you know you can do this
you can't do this you you know you can
go back um so I get it I get that
there's a lot of there's just so much so
I understand that we have a huge
undertaking within this committee
committee and then also within making
sure that we understand at least in my
mind that you know there's a difference
between ancestral and indigenous wisdom
which I feel was in some ways taken away
from us as a as a governing body as a
governing citizens of the United States.
But then also too um we have kept the
ancestral and indigenous wisdom which I
feel is not necessarily should be
something that's on my shoulders as an
indigenous person as a member of the
psilocybin advisory board but that is
something that should be distributed and
and shouldered amongst everybody because
we're from the state of New Mexico
because this medicine was here before
the state became a state. But with that
in mind, I feel that it's it's a part of
all of our quote duty to understand and
have respect for that. Bringing it
forward into,
you know, the people were here before
the state was here is my understanding.
These are where my opinions come in. The
state, the people were here, the wisdom
was here before the state became a
state. But we have also an obligation to
understanding that we are now citizens
of that state. We have a responsibility
to the rest of the community to to help
and understand and have that access so
that we can um move forward collectively
as a whole as a group um in this
fashion. Now comes in federal and you
know tribal governance 24 tribes here
recognized federally recognized in New
Mexico. That's a huge huge undertaking
and that's just looking at the Native
American indigenous populations. That's
not even looking at, you know, what it
um any other uh tribes that might be
represented here but don't have um a
reservation established res reservation.
Um and again going back to where I'm
coming from from Espanola area, you
know, what is that what is that equity?
What does that access look like? and
with respect to the populations that
really need to be reached and especially
in the far corners of the state, you
know, people who may not necessarily be
uh you know, I what I want is that
access to be available to the education
available to the outreach that goes into
these communities. Um, so again, it's
about brainstorming and honoring and
respecting all the hard work that
everyone has already been doing on on
the ground, grassroots efforts, reaching
out, calling tribal members. Um, that
work is insanely um, arduous and I've
had a little taste of that working for
the Navajo Nation before. Um, so
anyways, I will get off my soap box for
a bit. I just kind of wanted to just
throw at you, unfortunately throwing at
you um all that I'm hoping, but I
would love to start listening way to
anybody who has um who wants to speak
and I don't know how many people are we
do we have on here.
So, Desba, we have 15 attendees at the
moment outside of yourself and the
Department of Health staff that are
here. Um, so if you're ready though at
any point if anyone wants to raise their
hand, we can unmute you. You'll still
have to unmute it on your end and we'll
be more than happy to go ahead and
start.
>> Yeah, I think Yeah, go ahead.
>> Oh, I was just going to say we have
Matthew is the first to raise their
hand. Yeah, I think what I'm gonna do
for now is maybe have people just so we
I mean I do want to hear everybody, but
I want to also get to everybody. I'm
thinking maybe five minutes to get
through to see if everybody and then we
can go back around again if anyone has
any additional um things to say.
>> Okay, perfect. Okay, and Matthew, your
mic has been enabled. You'll just need
to go ahead and unmute. And to unmute,
just so everybody knows, is if you're on
the uh teams on the computer or on the
phone app, there's a small microphone
next to the camera icon. Just click on
that. And if you're on telephone only,
just press star six to mute or unmute.
And Matthew, you can go ahead and unmute
yourself.
Okay, just to check in, Matthew, we
can't hear you if you have unmuted. Um,
we do occasionally have individuals who
are uh who are not able to unmute.
Sometimes simply dropping off the
meeting and joining back in again works
for that.
So you may want to try that if you are
not able to unmute your mic otherwise.
The other item that we've we or the
other thing that we found sometimes is
sometimes individuals have the wrong mic
selected. If you want to try to select a
different mic next to the mic I uh icon
there is a little down arrow and you can
choose which microphone is used there.
And that though does depend on your own
home system.
>> Okay.
>> All right. Well, until someone else
wants to raise their hand, I'll go ahead
and from what I know and then please um
Dominic or uh Jorge or anyone um can
jump in and reverify it. But um so again
we are looking for two more more board
memories uh sorry board memories board
members um and as far as I know pe
people who are not in New Mexico can
participate in these committee meetings.
We are um going to be the chair
chairpeople and the slashboard members
um will be
uh working towards making sure that any
of the policies and regulations that we
are suggesting and recommending are
specifically for New Mexico citizens.
Um, but that, you know, if there's any
other uh input or observations that are
coming from the outside uh of New
Mexico, you know, we're welcome to
having other people join us and be on
the call because I think that this is
even though this is something that is in
New Mexico, it is so vitally important
for the people of the nation and
anything else that they're doing. um
maybe that there is some something else
that's going on in a different state or
in a different area that needs to be
looked at or considered um that may or
may not work with people here in New
Mexico. Um, and I think that that so far
as I my understanding of what we're
doing with that is important in that,
you know, this isn't this isn't just,
you know, we have a we have a
responsibility, I feel as citizens of
this particular state to
um, and what we're doing is that we're
we're shouldering that burden in some
ways for the future and that may be the
future of other states.
and what they're doing and what they're
looking at, but it's also collectively
where what we're doing here can take
effect in other places. Um I often kind
of look at it in terms of like the tiny
Buddha in the corner of the room that
even though we're not um
in that particular space that what you
what you do individually as a person and
then also within your community and then
also within your the bigger part the
state and the community can have greater
effect and change around the world. Um,
and I'm not saying that necessarily in
the ego sense of like New Mexico is so
wonderful and great, even though we are,
but it's just like what can we actually
do to help move this forward as a
nation? Um, and this is our this is this
is our time and our ability and our
responsibility to do it for us and for
others.
And please everybody if anyone else has
to like their thoughts on what I said
and want to have a discussion about
anything I said please I also look uh
encourage that. So I think
>> and Desba we do have Kate who uh Kate
your microphone has been is ready so go
ahead and unmute and you may speak.
>> Hi everybody. I'm Kate Hawk. I live in
Santa Fe now. Um, but I appreciate
hearing Desa hearing where you're coming
from and I agree. We may be just little
old New Mexico, but we are really um in
a position to be able to be leaders here
and to have learned from some of the
things that were done in other states um
and you know deal with our own
challenges and also our strengths. A
little bit of introduction. Before I
moved to Santa Fe, I lived in northern
Arizona on and next to the Navajo Nation
for 40 years. I was the director of the
Native American Trauma uh project going
back to the 90s. Started the Star
School, a Navajo Charter School, which
is still going there in our community.
And so I worked um a lot with, you know,
Native Americans, mostly from the Navajo
tribe, but some other tribes as well.
Um, you know,
Geez, looking at Colorado
as an example, I feel like New Mexico is
doing some things right, at least in the
language. Right up front, they
acknowledged indigenous communities
under, you know, accessibility.
Um, Colorado, it seemed like, well,
there was this legislation, it was voted
on, and then, oh, let's have some
indigenous people, um, have some
committee, and it was kind of an
afterthought. um you know, advisory
committees. It feels like this advisory
committee has some real power. Yes,
we're just advisory, but there's genuine
goodwill and wanting to learn and do the
best for everybody. Uh and in Colorado,
it seems like, you know, there there was
a 95page report written up um about, you
know, indigenous community committee
members. A lot of them weren't from
Colorado. I'm not sure how many were
from Colorado, but I know a lot of them
were not from Colorado.
And it seems like New Mexico has uh such
more of a tribal presence, organized
tribal communities, and you know, it
would be nice if there could be another
community committee member or two who
are from native communities or have
connections there. Um, which I don't,
but I'm willing to participate here. I
wanted to, you know, at least get in on
this first meeting and be happy to be an
active member. Um, so I just appreciate
that we're all getting started here and
I'm happy to be uh part of the
conversation.
>> Thank you, Kate.
>> And next we have Brett Phelps. Brett,
you should be unmuted or or just unmute
yourself and you can begin.
>> All right. Thank you guys. Yeah. And
thanks for your your help, Dominic. I
figured out for some reason my computer
does not like uh unmuting, so I hopped
to the phone real quick, so I didn't do
the what happened last time. Um, Desbod,
nice to meet you. Thanks so much for
leading this committee and, you know,
all your commitment to this. Um, so my
name is is Brett Phelps and I am an
attorney based out of Las Vegas, New
Mexico, but I live in Mora, New Mexico.
Um, so I'm very much concerned with the,
you know, the the issues in this
committee specifically about the the
access for rural frontier and
underserved areas. Um, and so just, you
know, I don't I don't know kind of what
the yeah, what the committee is looking
at as far as, you know, actually um
policy or rule recommendations or or
where, you know, if yeah, where we're,
you know, what the kind of process is
for that. But I did want to just kind of
put in some thoughts in terms of of a
couple of the points of responsibilities
for this um committee. You know,
specifically related to that, I think
there's a couple I I think there's a
couple things we can look at for access
in rural areas. Um number one is the the
teleaalth. You know, I think that's
something that uh I see it mentioned
here, so I know that's something we're
already looking at. But as much as we
can do on that is is going to be, you
know, to the to the benefit of of the
people in these rural areas, you know,
it's I think it's probably very likely
that a lot of the providers um the the
practitioners are going to be based in
um Albuquerque, Santa Fe, Los Cusus.
there may be some that end up in some of
these smaller areas. But um the more we
can enable that um and another thing
that I think would be really helpful,
you know, in terms of looking looking
forward at policy recommendations. Um
one thing that seemed to cause a lot of
problems in Oregon was the the location
designations for where the where the
therapy could be done and it had to be
in a dedicated facility for that. Um I
think looking at you know regulations
that as long as there's security and
safety measures in place that the
therapy can be done in um in other you
know in places that are used for other
purposes that aren't solely for um for
this this psilocybin therapy. I know
that's just something that has caused a
lot of issues with the Oregon program
and I think that could help a lot. um
you know, if we have places that are
already doing other kinds of therapy and
and that kind of work that want to
incorporate this, I I think that makes a
lot more sense than having to have
standalone places in you know, some of
these smaller communities. Um other last
recommendation and then I'll kind of
turn it over uh is on uh responsibility
number four here. Um the recommended
qualifications and process for
determination for the patient equity
fund. Um, seems like a great place to
start there is anyone who's receiving
any kind of state benefits. Um, if
you're Yeah. Um, if you're getting any
kind of, you know, food stamps,
financial assistance, Medicaid, um, that
seems like a great baseline for where to
kind of look at that. Um, you know, just
as maybe we can go broader than that,
but that seems like a a a very, you
know, solid place to start. Um, the the
other responsibilities I'm I'm very much
in support of. I like what you guys are
doing, but I am far from an expert in in
that kind of um in that kind of field.
So, you know, I'll be happy to as as
things move along to contribute my
thoughts or or anything I can do to, you
know, help any help the program in any
way going forward. Um but those are some
of the specific things that I think
could be really um helpful looking at,
you know, the actual rules that end up
being proposed by the board. Um, and
again, thanks to the Department of
Health, all you guys that are here, and
all the people taking their time to to
make this program work. Um, and that's
all I got for now. Thanks.
>> Thank you, Brett.
>> Thank you, Brett. And and Brett, just to
and for everybody else, just to
acknowledge one aspect is we have looked
a lot as far as what has occurred in
both Oregon and what is happening in
Colorado. And uh the the issue with
regard to locations was something that
even when the bill was proposed and was
brought up was very clear that it was
not going to be something restricted to
psilocybin only spaces. Uh that really
this is a tool to go into provider and
practitioner toolboxes. And so that is
not a restriction that is going to be
occurring here. Just so that everybody
is aware of that. That's something from
the very beginning that was being looked
at to ensure that we did not have that
barrier for individuals. So, just want
to make sure that's out there.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And it's it's come up a couple of
times, but uh it it bears repeating
because we do know that people are
hearing that as a big issue and barrier
in Oregon. And it is something that from
the very beginning was not going to be a
an aspect of the program here. So, yeah.
Anyway, uh the next person up is uh
Katherine Waro. Katherine, you're you
should be able to unmute your mic.
>> Hello, and uh thank you so much for
everybody for your time and effort in
this project. This is a very exciting
time for New Mexico. I am a licensed
professional counselor in Los Cusus, New
Mexico. Um, and I've been doing this
work for a few years very successfully
in helping people um, heal trauma.
Um, and obviously addressing the issues
that are uh, that this program was
designed for. Um, I guess I guess a
couple things I just want to say. I want
to share a story um that happened at a
integration group that I um,
was a part of. I hosted it with um an
indigenous um healer who we had people
from around the state attending. It was
an integration group around cannabis,
psilocybin and wuma.
And I just this there was a very
specific incident that happened that has
really stuck with me and I just wanted
to share it with everybody. There was an
individual in this group who spoke up
about how important um you know cultural
considerations are with respect to the
treatment. And this person talked about
how important it was to be able to have
a ceremony outdoors in a group with a a
you know a shaman facilitator and how
critical and important that was and how
they couldn't imagine being in an Airbnb
with an eye mask um you know etc. That
that felt really like awful and
something they would not consider. And
then somebody else shared and said, you
know, I actually did it exactly that way
and it was exactly what I needed. And I
can't imagine doing this outdoors with
strangers in a, you know, group setting.
And and I guess the reason I wanted to
share this story because it just stuck
with me is that we really need to be
very um careful about considering all
the options. I think no one way of
delivering this is going to work for
everybody. And I think it's really
important that we are really considering
the cultural aspect. Um, one of the
things that really worries me about the
way Oregon has been doing things is it's
very structured. It's very rigid. It's
usually in group settings with 30 to 50
people at one time, which means everyone
has to listen to the same music.
everyone has to have the same
everything, right? And I think it's
really important that when we're
designing this program that we're
looking at all the different ways
because like I said, I think what what
feels therapeutic and healing to one
person isn't necessarily going to feel
that same way to another person. And one
of the things that I think is really
really important about uh the program
that we establish is I think it needs to
be catered to the individual. I don't
think we can cater it to groups.
Meaning, I think that like if one person
needs a certain kind of music or a
certain, you know, with an eye mask or
outdoors versus indoors, I think we need
to have some flexibility in this program
to allow for that cultural component in
that everybody is going to feel safe in
different ways. Colonized white people,
they want clinical. they want it to feel
more sterile and more structured. Um,
but I I know that that's not going to
work for everybody. So, um, I know I'm
repeating myself at this point. I'm just
really passionate about this point. The
work the way I've been doing this um
work, I have been very much trying to
cater to individuals and I have found
that that has um resulted in the best um
outcomes. So, thank you very much for uh
your time. I would very much like to
help and participate. Um I I was though
thinking and so please correct me if I'm
wrong here, but I was thinking that the
board the subcommittee members probably
should be people of indigenous um you
know um descent. Um I I am a colonized
white person. I have a lot of privilege.
I recognize that I'm an ally. Um so I'd
like to help out in any way possible.
However, I I understand um that maybe,
you know, there are other subcommittees
that I might be more um suited for, but
I would I'm very interested in helping
out in any way possible. So, thank you
very much.
>> Thank you, Catherine.
Are there any other Looks like we don't
have any other people raising their
hands.
>> No, we do have one person who's on the
phone. Uh, Matthew, is it the 9237
number? The number ending in 9237. Oh,
yep. And it is. So, go ahead. Uh, and
you can unmute yourself on the phone to
unmute on a phone. It is star six.
Hello.
>> Hi.
>> Hello.
>> Hi. So, I tried to raise my hand earlier
and I was having some technical
difficulties. This is Matthew Armstrong.
>> Um,
>> thank thank you, Marthur. Matthew, we
can hear you now.
>> Okay. So, I'm a Lake Band superior um a
chipa um living here in New Mexico and
just some observational points because I
just I have watched all the meetings and
there's a couple things that I want to
make note of opportunity is when we hear
the word equity and access. I don't see
much talk about native uh African people
um and or
um indigenous afroentric. See, I feel
like black people would also benefit
greatly from from this due to the
traumas and the PS the PTSD of their
communities. And so I just feel like we
want to make this verbiage appropriate
for everybody. And then in another hand
while going through and studying for
this I've seen that there's an Iranian
woman of a descent who's using the word
indigenous because she's indigenous in
her own country. So I feel like there's
a lot of gray here and that's just my
take and thank you for listening to me.
Um I go by anomish my name is my native
name. you need anything or any more
points of view, I'm more than happy to
help.
>> Thank you.
>> Oh, sorry. Can you do you mind spelling
that out
if you're still able to unmute yourself?
>> Yeah. Can spell out what?
>> Your the name that you prefer to go by,
your indigenous name.
>> Uh, yes, ma'am. A N O M I S H
>> M O I
>> mean
>> it means big dog in Ojiway.
>> Thank you. Big witch.
>> Yes, ma'am.
>> Anybody else want to chime in here?
Hi, I can um yeah so I always imagine
this community um from like a healthcare
background we have this term called
social determinance of health um and so
that can include things like race,
income, education level, other aspects
that often co-mingle and can
indicate that a group needs assistance
because the society that they are in has
failed to adequately support them. And
so we have ended up with lower health
outcomes in these pe in these
populations.
And especially when you think about the
history that we took this medicine away
from them. I always imagine this
committee with um strong indigenous
support and um confirmation just from
the fact that we did we stole a lot of
their educ we re-educated them um took
away their culture. We had a horrible
horrible things happen. Um, and I
recognize that. And so I think, um, I
agree with the quote that the US states
are little laboratories of democracy
because they show that when we give the
people the choice and we elect the right
people, we can
kind of try to repair the damage that
our ancestors have done. And so I
appreciate um all input from all groups.
I wrote this to be broad because I think
that a lot of issues that are
experienced by um groups are often
caused by the systems that they are in
and so if we can build them correctly
then we can ensure that those problems
don't arise here.
I definitely agree and um I am open to
anyone kind of chiming in and having
further discussion for the next year.
But I'll get back on my soap box a
little bit just to kind of um go through
some of the uh points that people were
making um and then especially in I'll
start off with yours. I appreciate you
um saying that that was part of the
framework for why we were creating this
with such a broad you know equity,
access and cultural considerations and
to that point that exactly what you said
that it's not necessarily so much
sometimes I mean yes we have uh a focus
right we can have a focus with
indigenous cultures and so forth and I
don't want to miss the importance of
that specific thing
um And forgive me for using improper
terminology. You can totally call me on
it and say, you know, there's a better
way of using a certain term. Um, but
going back to the fact that, you know, I
grew up in Northern New Mexico where
both again to Ian's point and a little
bit to
Anomish, is that Anomish? um his point
was that you know we're such a
uh
isolated in some ways area right both
with the language and the cultural
aspects because the Spanish had come in
and you know found this indigenous
people that were there and a lot of that
language is no longer a part of the
current colloquial language is Spanish
it's ancient ancient Spanish that people
use um
that that a lot of what was taken away
from indigenous people in the area is
their own culture and it was I don't
want to say replaced with but it was
colonized to the sense of like you are
no longer indigenous, you are Spanish,
you are white for the sake of being a
part of New Mexico because New Mexico
has its agenda to move forward and we're
going to bypass that. That's not
something that I want to be having
happen again with this project, with our
with our program in in the sake of
moving forward with something. We're
going to bypass once again indigenous
and cultural considerations and that
access and we're just moving forward
without consideration to you. I feel
like that in itself has been a part of
the trauma which I go back to and say
that it's not necessarily all on my
shoulders as an indigenous person that I
ensure and I make sure and I'm again
retokenized to some degree that it's up
to me. It is all up to us as far as our
responsibility to be here in this
program and it part of the community as
we choose as our time allows and the
rest of our responsibilities in the rest
of our lives to bring up the things that
are important because in that sense it's
like if we had the answers to everything
either as a group or as a whole or as
people in general we wouldn't be in the
place that we are right now. We wouldn't
be having to understand and relearn.
That's part of the beauty of listening
to other people and coming up because
there's something that we missed or you
know the agendas that we trying to move
forward. We're we're hoping at least I'm
hoping that we can listen to everything
and everyone as much as possible so that
we can go from a fractured state to a
healed state. uh kind of similar to the
Japanese way of like you know the
creating the vessel again with all the
crocs and stuff in it. Um,
and and so by listening to that, I'm I'm
I'm here to listen, but it's also, you
know, I know I hear non-natives saying,
you know, it's not my place to have to
say something or and and I get that and
I and I and I honor that you respect and
are aware of who you are and what you
bring. And your awareness in itself
speaks volumes because if you didn't
already know you wouldn't be saying that
in saying that you know your place in in
that way is the awareness and that
respect to that like maybe someone else
should should do it right. Um but also
to that to that um
point
um you know I also too am limited in my
ability to be quote indigenous as I'm
also to relearning my cultural because
it was also taken away from my family
and um I've come back to my indigenity
through medicine that was provided from
a non-native you know setting or area,
you know,
and I honor the fact because because
sometimes the truth and the message
needs to be provided through that
vessel.
To me, it's the me it's the medicine,
it's the message, it's the love and the
care that's saying regardless of the
carrier and the messenger, I'm providing
this message because it's important.
And sometimes I feel that depending on
the you know that person that
messengergers's agenda might get in the
way right but it is that person stepping
back and saying I am just a vessel and a
messenger for this message and for the
medicine to provide to you because it is
that important.
It is so important that we all need to
hear it and and so in that way I want to
listen to all aspects because there
might be something that I miss because
maybe my my training of of how I'm in
this world might be quote too white. Um,
and by that I mean,
you know, I was talking to my dad some
time ago about something else and I
said, you know, that was that's a very
like non-navalent thinking. And he's
like, it is. And I was like, yeah, it
is. And he had to I had to help stop
himself and to kind of reflect and
become aware
of the thing that he was saying. And so
therefore, I'm saying I'm offering this
too to everyone else. I want to be able
to listen. One of the things that I have
come across in my own, and I've heard
this from other people too, other native
people, and I apologize. I jump around a
lot, and so you know, um, you can call
me on that. You can call me on anything.
Uh,
and, um,
she said, uh, it sometimes it's hard to
gather and get all the the natives
together into, you know, agreeing. And I
will say this, this is this is probably
one of the harder aspects of working
with another group which is working on
my Dark Wind show was, you know, trying
to come to consensus about how we put
the story from the page to the screen
because everybody's right. Everybody has
their opinion of like what exactly needs
to be in there and it's all conflicting.
Um, and to get on the same page, I know
that that's very important and that
might seem in some ways trivial then to
what the importance of this particular
committee is doing, but I see that, you
know, in other instances. And so that's
why I'm saying, you know, it's it's good
to be able to have different voices and
and listening is so important. um having
these discussions whether or not it's
like someone has a very strong opinion
about one thing and then it's very
opposite polar opposite in another I
think is also important to listen to as
to why because maybe there's something
that's being overlooked um in pursuit of
moving something forward.
Um,
but you know, back to uh, you know, what
Katherine was saying, yes, I think
that's important just to kind of say
this. You know, that it's not anything
that needs to be said is is important.
And then also there's to me a level of
priority of what needs to be happening
for this committee is like things that
are urgent and emer, you know, emergency
is very important. Um, and also like
maybe not so important but urgent and
then so forth. if anyone's familiar with
the Frank co I think Franklin Kovi you
know quadrant square and then there are
some things that are you know you know
we can kind of maybe not put that up
higher um but for me it's also a matter
of figuring out what are the key
components are there like three pillars
is there five pillars that really need
to be understood as far as what needs to
be moved forward or important um to
outline and um and
a process of getting that onto the page
and then again to the committee.
So when it comes to again like what I in
was saying as far as the equity and
access of the different cultural
considerations within that community in
that framework um I also hear what Brett
was saying um about you know spa places
like Moa you know also very isolated how
does that look that might be a place
that's a setting for you know a place
that that's a community gathering space
outside kind of to Katherine's point
where it's it's not something that's
necessarily structured, but I feel like
allowing um what that particular place
needs and what that, you know, and and
then maybe even though someone says, and
I don't know what this looks like, but
if we have someone who really needs to
have more clinical setting, would they
be able to then have access to that
space where an outdoor setting is all
that Modok is is able to offer? But is
there a place that's within that has one
or the other? Is that something that we
need to look at too where people at
least have two options in a specific
rural area? What does that look like?
Um, and of course what I'm hearing from
Dominic is that there's really not going
to be such a rigid um determination of
like what that space looks like because
I feel like I know um
there of I'm not sure exactly which my
brain is not helping me right now, but
they're looking at how to the set and
setting of these trials which is why
they're asking for input from different
specific groups, one-on-one interviews
with women who have faced trauma. Um um
first first responders and um army vets
who have experienced PTSD. Um I think
that they already have enough input from
that particular group for these clinical
trials and what those look like because
that set and setting is really
important. And then also especially
especially um the integration portion
you know how are we having um services
established? you know, I know that they
it's a completely different um
project, but the wraparound services for
um juvenile offenders, I'm familiar with
that one from um they were trying to
implement it in northern New Mexico. I
think it works in Santa Fe, but how how
do we have community involvement where
we're allowing the community to heal
itself as opposed to just throwing this
the student the kids away in three-hour
detention centers that, you know, are
not a part of their community? How can
the community really come and and help
itself
um take on that responsibility and
accountability for yes, this is a part
of our problem and these are our
brothers and sisters, these are our
family members regardless of it's
through blood, it's through community
and networking ties.
Um
but yes, so that's my soap box. I don't
know if anyone else had any other things
that they wanted to chime in. I think I
see James.
>> Yes.
>> Yes. And James, you can unmute yourself
and go ahead and speak.
>> Hello everybody. My name is James and
I'm from Arizona and I've had the honor
of working in the addiction medicine
realm and we worked closely with Native
Americans ranging from the Hila River
Indian community, the Yavapai Apache
Nation, Achin, and as well as the White
Mountain Apache tribe. And through these
experiences that I've had, a lot of
people were impacted by severe alcohol
use disorders and methamphetamine. It's
rampant in the um in the reservations.
And I personally witnessed how the
stigma, the geographic isolation, and
the limited resources can really
compound.
And it is absolutely terrible the
stories that I've heard. And I really
praise and honor this community to
really carefully and respectfully give
praise and actually help people that
really need it the most. Um I really
liked how you had mentioned Desba the
Japanese saying of wabishabi. It's
looking at the beauty of imperfection
and how can we look at such an imperfect
system and try to make it beautiful
again. And I really respect that. One of
the things that I really uh would love
to hear uh thoughts and opinions about
and kind of echoing what Brett had to
say earlier is location.
Travel and transportation is very
difficult for many people. And if we
have designated areas that are very far
from somebody, then that means that
we're limiting access to people that
might need it the most. And so I'm all
open ears, but trying to make this as
accessible as possible with v varying
locations and working with local tribes
and their uh public health um um areas
would definitely be something that I'd
be for. So, thank you for giving me the
time to speak and I really um applaud
everybody for being here. This is very
important.
Thank you, James.
>> I don't see any other hands up. Is there
anyone else who would like to speak?
And again, to raise your hand, you just
need to click on the little hand icon
near the top of the team's window if
you're on a computer. If you are on um
the phone it is press star five to raise
your hand
>> and maybe um I'm not sure to the extent
of like what this committee that this
time in this space or this meeting is
Dominic but you know it's it it seems
that at least from what I'm hearing from
both James and from Brett in that space
Brett was mentioning something about tea
health um And you know to me it seems
like this is the place in where we would
figure out what would be the best
recommendation for kind of figuring
these things out is when I hear
tellaalth and I'm hearing set and
setting and I'm hearing isolation
geographic isolation
um and then also what I'm thinking about
and this might also reach into other
committees as well is you know the
facilitation of of these things Um where
where that committee and our committee
can can cross over is how we provide a
recommendation to
the administrator or facilitator for
these particular things. Like what does
that look like? And is that a matter of
providing or finding funding for a
traveling facilitator, someone that is
able to be able to work with an
individual in that particular space,
especially depending on order of
magnitude of their uh need, you know,
and then and that that goes more into
wherein I'm thinking is the dosage and
the setting, etc. Is that kind of where
I feel like there's crossover, more room
for talk as board members andor trying
to figure out how we're making sure that
we provide a safety net for this
program,
>> right? So, Desba, that's that's actually
a great point and tellaalth has been
something again that has actually been
being looked at since the beginning of
the program. And just to give an idea,
for example, with the current medical
cannabis program, the um the evaluations
that providers are doing with their
patients, those can often be done
through teleaalth. And so we do envision
that there'll be that aspect as well.
What all of the details for that will be
for those evaluations, we'll see with
recommendations with regard to tellaalth
during actual journeys, that is probably
going to look very different and need to
have individuals there. I do see
Katherine's raised her hand again. So,
Katherine, I'll just, uh, say a little
bit more and then I'll defer to you a
little bit here. Um, but, uh, as far as
from an equity and an access standpoint,
it does need to be looked at as far as
how do we get that access in those rural
communities and ensure that it's there.
Um a as far as the equity fund that
again that will be determining what are
the requirements for how that funding
should be dispersed and how that funding
you know who will be eligible for it,
what considerations there are that can
include a wide variety of things. Not
just um you know for example income so
socioeconomic status but also could als
include geography and some aspects with
that. For example, how far do people
have to travel? Is there some sort of
reimbursement needed for travel expenses
uh for being able to for patients to be
able to stay, you know, uh with housing,
you know, temporary housing and hotels,
that sort of thing when they are
traveling for their treatments. Um those
are different things that this committee
can be looking at and helping with
regard to the um the the
recommendations. In addition, there is
going to definitely be overlap with
several of the other committees and
definitely anticipate that to occur. Um,
and one thing that did come up in the
other committee meeting this morning is
one of the things the department will do
as part of our administrative support is
when there are those kinds of questions
or recommendations to other committees,
we will ensure that they get on over to
the chair of that committee so that they
can be raised and brought up during
their committee meetings as well so that
there can be that cross-pollination
which by the way does not mean that
people from one committee cannot either
attend or serve on another committee. In
fact, we do encourage it. That kind of
cross-pollination is actually, I think,
going to be very important as to the way
things move forward with that. Um, shall
I move on to Katherine?
Okay, Katherine, go ahead. You should be
uh you should be able to unmute.
>> Uh, thank you, Dominic. And actually,
uh, you spoke to it um after I'd already
raised my hand, but I will go ahead and
elaborate. Um based on the work I've
been doing for about three years now
being that I am in Los Cusus um I do end
up using teleahalth quite a bit for the
preparation for the integration
afterwards. Um and I do agree uh Dominic
that during the journey it would not be
appropriate to just use teleaalth. Um I
think we could incorporate teleaalth
meaning if there is a person that can be
present and maybe then online in
addition that's an option. I think that
would be definitely something we'd need
to like work some of the kinks out a
bit. Um but I can just say that um the
prep work and integration has been very
successful using teleaalth. Um I in
addition I have a um a meeting the day
before a journey at the location with
the client in order for them to
establish set and setting the day before
so there's nothing new on the day of um
so I would say though that for the the
if if if other people decide to
implement that same structure which I
don't know if that's going to happen or
not but I will tell you it makes a huge
difference in allowing their anxiety to
be relieved the night before. Um, I do
think those both will need to be in
person. I don't think there's a way to
get around that. I think that um there's
a lot more details I can talk about
later, but this is an area where I feel
like I can really contribute and
participate. So, thank you.
>> Thank you, Catherine.
>> Yeah, go ahead, Dominic. Oh, I was just
going to say and Matthew had put into
the chat and I just want to make sure
that for those who aren't able to see
the chat very well if they're on phones
or other items um he wanted to add that
equity should be considered from a
patient and facilitator with the facil
facilitator aspect meaning not just uh
who and how treatment is equitable but
how do we make sure that it's applied to
the people who heal within their
communities and have experience but not
a medical background.
So
>> yes,
>> just wanted to make sure that was there.
>> Yes, thank you. That's that's another
good point too. Um and that's I think
that's also might be overlap into
training as well. Maybe perhaps because
that is how do we take care of the
healer, you know, how do the healers
take care of themselves, right? How does
that, you know, what does that look like
when it comes to trainings as well as
certifications? Who's going to be able
to be the facilitator and or
administrator? um in these particular
ways. Um so that might be of an interest
if you go to the different committee um
links that are going to be available. I
think training is also one of them. I
think it it's the the last one so far
before we have our board meeting, but um
um I'll go back to Katherine's point in
just a second. Um
but to yeah to that you know the
accessibility to us I think at so far at
the end we can have a space where you
know if there are things that people
wanted to email the group about with
regard to each of the committee
meetings. Um we could probably have that
in there where it's the subject line is
the committee meeting you know what date
of the meeting it was etc. and just so
that we have that kind of collective and
then we can all be able to look at what
the notes are, the questions are and
have that for reference when we have our
board meetings. Um that's the way that
people can access the group is through
the psilocybin I think email um that
will be provided at the end. Um but then
also just being able to sign up for the
email news blasts um that we have about
future um board meetings that we will
have. Um but yes to Katherine's point,
yes, exactly. Um
this is this is the whole point of it.
You know, there are people who are doing
the groundwork as Kate had mentioned
before, she had done extensive work um
in Arizona with the Navajo Nation before
and you see things and even though it's
as an outside perspective, but it's also
within the perspective. Um my ex-husband
is is non-native. He lives out on the
reservation. He's a school teacher. Um,
and he has a different perspective than
I do. He's in the thick of it. He sees
and he knows. He's got ears of what's
going on. And whether or not like he has
a non-native perspective,
he's there. He is um he's witnessing
what's going on. And that's not for
nothing. But then also too, we have and
I'm and I want to make sure that we do
emphasize that we have other cultural
considerations such as what uh I'm sorry
I'm going to pronounce your name wrong.
I'm going to try not to. Uh let's see.
Did I have it in here?
Anomish
um was saying about you know
Afroindigenous that has also been
another neglected aspect you know of of
indigenous culture on on the whole what
does that look like I had my first
encounter with Afroindigenous cultures
out on in Massachusetts you know the
Wampaoag
um and it was very it was just so
interesting to me um but that is again a
result of, you know, intermingling um
assimilations and cross-cultural
um teachings that we can all share. And
often times we see that some teaching
that we have in a different culture,
there's there's a mirror somewhere else
in a different culture that we might
have neglected. And it all does come
from an indigenous place. At some point,
we have all been indigenous in our
ancestors at some point, whether we're
here now, whether we stayed close to the
land. But I feel like returning to the
land through the medicine, through the
work of figuring that out is part of the
healing, of returning to our ancestors.
And that's where the medicine is all
bringing us together for that purpose.
Um,
let's see. I think we have someone
else's hand up.
>> Yes. Uh, next is Brenda uh Burgard.
Brenda, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
>> Hello everyone. I'm Brenda Burgard. Uh,
thank you Desba and Dominic for having
this meeting. This is really super
important, I think. Uh, little
background about myself. I am on the
advisory board for teaching and
training. And I just wanted to say just
wanted to add a little bit here. I'm
primarily a teleaalth um therapist and
um I found that uh what Katherine was
saying earlier is uh deadon. Just having
that um training about teleaalth and
psychedelics is really important to
reach out to the community. And I was
thinking uh there could maybe be a
possibility um doing primarily teleaalth
with um a patient like somewhere in New
Mexico and then maybe um the therapist
themselves could travel to the
individual uh because I I deal primarily
with a lot of people who are homebound
uh because of uh physical disabilities
or again That trans transportation issue
is a big one because that's why I
provide tellahalth because many people
don't have access to a bus system or a
car or even a relative to drive them
somewhere and then the expense of of um
a hotel or uh possibly having
accommodations for people. So uh I think
that's going to be a really big one. Um
and and not to say uh people would want
to have a um a ceremonial type of of
you know um therapy or uh maybe a hybrid
of a little bit of both. But uh like you
were saying Dominic uh this is going to
be a real mix hybrid of different things
for different individuals and I think we
are doing a service to meeting people
where they're at. Um so thank you very
much.
>> Thank you Brenda. And then also to that
point, you know, I'm hearing this kind
of coming up um
with the teleaalth and the and the
geographic isolation, but also societal,
not necessarily uh geographical
isolation, but um the transportation
issue.
Um,
and this I feel like if if some of you
who are on the call haven't already
known each other and know who you are,
this I think is a great time to make
sure to reach out so that these are
networks if you have I mean New Mexico
is such a broad broad area. Um, and I
know that another friend I'm I I wish
that they were on the call today. Um,
but it's just, you know, what does that
look like when you're reaching out to um
the groups? And maybe Kate can also talk
to a little bit about this if she if she
chooses to, she's still on here. Um but
I know that was it was years ago
is while this is while it's been brought
up to me about make making sure that we
understand indigenous
um aspect of this committee and or just
in general
there is the aspect of federal tribal
federal government tribal sovereignty
federal treaties and their
responsibilities for the federal for the
uh for the tribes. That brings up an
issue of tribal governance and that's
where I definitely
not quite sure what that actually really
looks like. But I do know that as far as
like grassroots
individual programs within a nation,
that might be the place. Which goes back
again to the networking, which goes back
to knowing who is out there for
recommendations.
as a therapist, massage therapist, you
know, it's important to know what other
people's work is like. So that when you
can't take care of somebody, you know
who else to send them to that can be
able to provide the service that they
need or you're not a roer or you're not
like a myofascial release person. you
know the people within your network who
you can send um and and recommend them
to or you know the benefits of you know
a chiropractor or any other kind of
physical therapist you know the other
therapists and the work that they do so
that you can make sure that again there
is that safety net um and where our
travel and our outreach might be really
important um and I'm not saying that
anybody is I'm just you know throwing
this out there that, you know, by
keeping ourselves precious to what we
the work that we do and not knowing who
else is out in our field and what kind
of work that they do. Maybe someone is
brilliant at clinical settings and
making someone feel really comfortable
with their first journeys or, you know,
with this particular thing. Someone else
might be really amazing at doing
one-on-one individual work. and there's
might be someone else who can handle you
know a group of 50 people even though
that might not be like the most
beneficial setting. Um
but I think that you know understanding
where those people are by networking by
having these conversations by knowing
and then also too um bringing this out
more to light so we have these
conversations with our families if we
haven't already um over our our meals
about the work that they're we're doing
and why this is important. I feel like
that's another aspect of this as well is
you know being able to have those
conversations out in the open more so
rather than um you know that we can be a
little more open about it. This is
something that's really important for
our health. You know if you don't
destigmatize something then you it can't
be a part of our everyday appearance
because again it was so considered
taboo. Completely different analogy
women's women's health
you know, menration, that sort of thing.
We don't talk openly enough about these
these this this very normal instance of
our own bodies and what they're going
through. We're too ashamed to talk about
these things. And why is it a shame to
talk about our traumas, our griefs, our
process, the things that we're trying to
go through in our life and the things
that we need to to do and the lengths um
medicines that we we go for for help.
Um, but we need to have these more as a
conversation, you know, in in our
everyday life. Um, and I and I know that
I haven't necessarily experienced that
so much. It's mostly with the people
that I know, but you know, we finding
that education and that outreach could
just be one-on-one, but it also is in
our networking and knowing who who are
our allies and who is good at at certain
individual things. um when it comes to
our health. Let me see just read the
uh
was I think we can all agree prep can be
tellalth. Yeah.
Requirements for education lensure will
need to be determined. Yes. So there's
still a lot of of instances and those
are really good points to bring up as
far as like what what each of these
things looks like. Um, so when we're
when we're finding out what those
requirements are for our trainings, you
know, um I think that there's several I
was trying to participate in a training
before, but I um for Colorado and they
do have um certain requirements funding
even to renew my own license as a
massage therapist. And I know that
that's completely different for everyone
else in their own respective
professions. um how much the cost is to
to get started. Um and then also what
does that look like? But then again,
those considerations of that it should
make sure um I think I think part of it
is just making sure that on the side of
equity and access and cultural
considerations that the recommendation
from here that moves into the overlap of
other trainings and so forth is what
that actually possibly looks like as far
as making sure that it is
cost-effective, efficient, um not
overburdening with with um on both sides
to the provider and the um patient. How
does that look like? But making sure
that it is congruent be between the two.
Um but yes, you know, tellahalth, it
seems like that is something that it
it's
it's um cross referencing to both.
>> And
Kate has her has their hand up.
>> Y
>> So Kate, you should be able to unmute
yourself.
Kate, we do it does seem that There we
go. Okay, go on ahead, Kate.
>> Yeah, sorry, I I accidentally turned my
audio off in the process of trying to
get on technology. Um yeah, just uh
building on what you were saying about
um you know relevant to Colorado. I did
my Colorado
natural medicine facilitator training
and part of it was just to understand
the system and to be prepared for what
we're doing here. But when I I went
through the training and then I don't
think I'm going to
complete, you know, all of the
supervision and everything to be a
Colorado facilitator because it would
require going to the licensed places
which can cost $500 a day or more for a
setting that might not be the setting I
really want to work in. and also
accessing the mushrooms which are
hundreds of dollars a dose and some
people have said they weren't really the
quality that even though they're you
know through the system but they weren't
the best quality. So, as we go ahead,
you know, thinking about especially uh
communities that have limited resources,
uh I'm really happy to hear today that
this from the beginning. Uh we've New
Mexico has looked at uh you know, not
requiring all the same restrictions that
Colorado has. Uh and especially in in
native communities, just thinking about
well, what are appropriate settings
then? Is it going to be anywhere and
just up to the facilitators or are there
going to be some kind of qualifying
conditions or at least recommendations
um for those settings?
Just wanted to comment on that. Thank
you.
>> Thank you, Kate. And uh just so that
everybody knows I actually just pulled
this on up um because since there is a
lot of questions regarding tellaalth and
I'm putting it on into the chat um but
um essentially there already are uh
protocols as far as uh and and what is
actually considered appropriate with
regard to telea medicine and tellaalth
and so I'm actually going to share the
document that Medicaid has and with one
exception on it as far as the provider
residing outside of New Mexico. I think
that this actually fits in very well.
And so the thing to remember is we don't
necessarily have to reinvent the wheel
when we're looking at a lot of this. A
lot of this is already in place. We just
need to make sure that as it moves
forward that it is going to be equitable
and accessible for uh individuals. And
so it should be able to uh go to that
link. And that shows again this was uh
through turquoise care through the
healthcare authority um that actually
published this earlier um this year and
it actually shows what the requirements
are for tele medicine um prioritizing
some options and then of course for
turquoise care in and of itself how they
help to promote tele medicine but uh and
again the only thing in here that may be
a little bit problematic with regard to
the psilocybin act itself is the
provider that are residing outside of
New Mexico. But again, that's a
determination to be made uh in the
regulations.
Anyway, uh it looks like uh Ian, I think
you are next on with your hand up.
Yeah, I just wanted to let you know um
so if you want you can make a
recommendation to like another committee
so we could vote to say um that prep can
be available by tellahalth and then you
can make that recommendation to them.
They'll take it, turn it into patient
safety approved language, and then that
will get sent to the board if you would
prefer to do it that way.
>> Are you speaking to me and or to
everyone else as well?
>> Yeah. So, I'm speaking to you as chair
cuz you would transmit the vote on
what we were doing. So if we were saying
tellah health should prep can be
acceptable and then we as the like
patient safety and qualification
committee would go and say okay we got
this from them let's make sure it also
aligns with our or crosses with our
domain and that way it's checked off by
both
>> okay
>> or if you leave it more vague then the
specialization can be done by the
patient safety because that would fall
or I mean training and education because
that would fall under their jurisdiction
and so forth.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And then so what I'm hearing from
Dominic is that essentially from this
document that you provided that everyone
has access to within the chat um the New
Mexico Medicaid tele medicine that the
language from this essentially but
without the outside
uh
just that last part. So it says tele
medicine service requirements and then
there's four bullet points and it says
if provider if if provider resides
outside of New Mexico must be licensed
in New Mexico. So that one essentially
for example
struck out and essentially like the this
whole document itself could be a basis
for that tele medicine consideration.
>> Yeah. Uh I'm just putting it up on the
shared screen for people to be able to
see and that is correct desa and so it's
not necessary that uh an entire new
teleaalth policy be written it's already
actually a part of the normal regular
procedures for behavioral health medical
care. Uh and again the only thing with
regard to it is just again based upon uh
what is what what is being determined as
we move through the regulations is the
provider being uh in New Mexico might be
the only restriction or additional
restriction that might be needed with
regard to this. Um and and that's again
where we say is a lot of times um we
don't necessarily need to reinvent the
wheel because it's already here. that
the process is already here. The
question just comes down to will the
program will the services be allowed to
be delivered through tellaalth and
exactly which services it will be. But
the actual mechanisms uh around
tellaalth don't need to be determined
and it looks like Brett uh has his hand
up. Um, so Brett, if you would like, you
can unmute yourself.
>> Yeah, thank you, Dominic. Um, sure. I'm
glad, yeah, glad we're having the such a
good conversation on the health telealth
side. Um, and I I may be, you know,
somewhat of an outlier here based on on
what I'm hearing um, from other folks,
but, you know, I do think it's worth
considering that there may be there may
be circumstances where the entire
process could be handled through
teleaalth, you know, at the discretion
of the provider. Obviously, that's not
going to work for everyone. Um, but I
think it's something that that is worth
considering and specifically looking at
these, you know, Medicaid requirements.
um or service requirements. The one
that's bolded in the tele medicine
service requirements is no restrictions
on services that can be offered via
teleaalth. Um so if we're you know
translating that into this program um I
think it is something that you know
could yeah and you obviously got to put
proper safeguards in place but I I don't
know that it needs to you know
automatically be ruled out from the from
the jump or or unless you know unless
there's there's yeah strong reasons for
it that y'all have said but I think it's
worth considering that in in certain
circumstances you know it may be
appropriate for Um, yeah, for the the
entire process to be done through
tellahalth, again, I do think that would
increase the the equity. Um, but I
obviously, like I said, I know I'm an
outlier on that, but I just wanted to
throw that out there while we're having
this discussion. So, thanks.
>> Thank you, Brett. And I think that's a
good point um that you bring up and uh
in the sense that that's a good that's a
good point. Um I think for this
particular session since it is the first
one um and I do want to get input more
also um from the um
Wednesday night meeting um from other
people but I'll I'll bring this into
that session is that okay this is some
this is a good kind of like starting
point that we can kind of start getting
having a conversation
which is what I'm hoping for is like
okay this is what we are recommending
and this is what we're you know point to
consider and this is a good place um
like as an example because that good
point no restrictions on services can be
offered through teleaalth
and this is where I would you know argue
along with anyone else too that you're
right uh I I think that the teleaalth
portions as Katherine had suggested in
the beginning
uh evaluation what is the evaluation
portion particular look like and um then
this is something that I guess would go
into cross-pollinating with the board.
What does those evaluations look like?
What does that look like as far as
equity? But as a starting point, let's
look at tele medicine, New Mexico
Medicaid and the language that's there
and adopt, you know, 99% of it with the
exception of these two lines. those ones
need to be looked at um further and we
need to figure out what would either
replace it and or augment it in some
ways. Um but yeah, the restrictions on
that for instance for the sake of
conversation
that's that would be definitely like a
point of conversation through the
journey section of that regarding equity
and access, but also taking into
consideration
um the importance of quote ancestral and
indigenous wisdom where
this is
that might be something that a um
a facilitator might you know in regards
to regulations in medicine you know how
far does the government step in right to
to say what is acceptable and not. And
um again, this is just for the sake of
conversation and argument is, you know,
there might be some people who can
handle a a journey on their own. And I'm
not to say who those people are, but
maybe that is something for a later
conversation with the evaluation of the
person. But I also don't want to be on
the side I want to air on the side of
caution
where it would be better that before
that happens that say like the release
of the the the one-on-one patient um
therapist model or facilitator
administrator model is that that at
least closes out
I don't know I don't know what that
looks like again this is probably a
cross-pollination trainings facilitator
conversation.
Um, but it is a good place to kind of
look at this is when we start getting
into the weeds of the language of what
really is something that you know what
is the care of our community and
especially for me and I'm thinking about
these isolated areas. Um, I would want
to rather heir on the side of caution
especially when it comes to the care of
our communities. Um, and I feel like
that one-on-one
um, facilitator administering
um, journey setting is invaluable and in
some ways necessary. So that's just kind
of putting a pin in it. That's the kind
of conversation that we can definitely
have. That's where I feel like, you
know, really fine-tuning what these look
like, putting a giant pin in this as far
as something to go back to and make sure
that we have um straightened out and and
and before, you know, December 30th,
2026, you know, we've had a chance to
really look at it and evaluate what that
really looks like when it comes to
adopting policies that are already, you
know, provided and what that looks like
um I think someone else might have had
something to say or
Catherine.
Yeah. Um I just wanted to say that I
think I think Dominic kind of addressed
it a little bit in the chat where you
know there's certain things you can't do
on tellahalth. I mean you can't do
surgery on tellahalth. there are certain
limitations right and I think like as a
practitioner I would not be comfortable
doing it on tellahalth I I wouldn't do
it so um I I just feel like it it the
whole definition of the way therapeutic
use of the medicine is it requires
providing like safety and and being
present to be able to address their
needs help them to the restroom you know
there's things that need to be done. And
so I get that this is probably a
conversation for later, but I just can't
let that comment go without at least
weighing in back on the the side like
I've been doing this for 3 years. I
would never ever be comfortable doing
this via tellahalth. There's other um
psychedelics that I would be comfortable
doing. Um MDMA is one of them, but
definitely not psilocybin and especially
not for somebody who um you know doesn't
have any experience with the medication.
I think that people can do this
medication on their own. I call that
recreational use and it can be done in a
therapeutic way, but it's not it's not
psilocybin assisted therapy. So, I just
I just think that there's I think it
would be very dangerous for us for
safety standpoint to not have somebody
present to keep the people safe. You
know, one of the big stigmas that I've
been having to work with since I've been
doing this work is people are terrified.
Am I going to jump out of a window and
am I going to run out into traffic?
Like, these are things that I hear all
the time. And if you don't have somebody
there with them, um, you know, there's
just some things that I think we're just
going to have to um, you know, look at
from a safety point of view. So, that's
my two cents. Thanks for listening. Um,
appreciate everybody. Yeah, thank you,
Katherine. And I think you're you're
definitely not alone in those in those
um concerns. And that's again, you know,
for the sake of conversation, just kind
of pointing that out. Um because this is
this is a this is a good time. What I'm
hoping for also too with these
committees is it's not I I love you all.
You're you're all amazing. I really want
to also broaden it to the general
public. I really want it to be people
who are curious and be like, "Oh, what
are what's New Mexico doing? Why do they
think that's so important? I, you know,
I think that's bogus or whatever it is.
I want these people in the conversation,
you know, to to even just listen in and
hear what we're having to talk about
because there's so much. And this is
just one committee. Um, you know, I want
people to kind of come in and see and
understand, you know, like why is that
so important? Why is that a concern? Why
is that, you know, why are they having
this discussion? you know, and and
really seeing the importance of why
we're trying to carefully look through
this. Um,
and and so, you know, I know that, you
know, we're only specifically talking
about psilocybin and therapeutic use,
medical setting, etc. You know, I think
I just briefly saw someone say something
in the chat here. Let me check it.
And
people use this medicine in therapeutic
countries. It is not recreational. Just
because a therapist isn't there. Well,
this is true. And again, this is all
really good conversation. Um the comment
was it's just because someone's using it
by themselves, it's not recreational.
It's also therapeutic. And I do agree on
that. Again, opinions aside and etc.
Um these are all good times to have
conversation. I know. I can't remember
which um I think it's Iasa. I'm not sure
which one it is, but anyways, outside of
this committee, you know, no, I think
it's I think it's um maybe it is
mushrooms. I can't remember. One of them
13 years old. It's a right of passage
when the children go into, you know, to
become a member a functioning member of
their society. 13 years old. My kid is
13. I'm like, that's not something that
I feel like, you know, I I that's not
the culture that I was raised in. That's
not how I feel comfortable. If I was a
part of that culture, it would be
something that that would be a part of
of my teaching, right? This is this is
not what we're doing here. Every other
place has their own understanding. And
so that's where we all have to kind of
get onto the same page as far as like
what is the therapeutic medical uh
settings or use and how is the
government actually going to provide
that space and that structure and that
framework. there might be things that
fall outside of that and I don't want to
say we're not going to talk about that
but it is you know we can't sometimes
pull some of those things into but but
to that point again back to this is
where it is a little bit um I don't want
to say difficult let's just say a
challenge uh where the ancestral
indigenous wisdom comes from right it's
not always necessarily recreational if
say uh someone outside is micro doing or
what does that even look like? What is
the threshold? What is that, you know,
is is the micro doing based on um the
therapist, the facilitator,
administrator, the person. Someone could
probably see that like a gram is a micro
dose. Other people are like sensitive
to.3 of a gram. Again, back to dosaging,
what that's going to look like, how
that's going to be regulated, what are
those systems going to be in place. But
back to Katherine's point, yes, some of
these everybody handles things
differently. Um and we have to make sure
that we are allowing to have a safe
space that this is a safe space and that
there are certain amount of regulations
when it comes to it. um and you know
administering facilitating someone's
journey especially and especially if
it's going to be and I'm assuming a lot
of this is going to be for the first
time because this is going to be the
first time that someone has an
opportunity to sit with the medicine and
there are a lot of questions I had a lot
of questions um and honestly some of
them didn't get answered you know right
away and you know but for some people,
they're going to need to research
absolutely thoroughly be beyond, you
know, they're going to, this could take
years of them researching. It could take
years of them feeling safe enough and
feeling comfortable enough. It takes the
right facilitator, the right place. Um,
they might be limited to the options
that they have. you know, Brett might be
the only person that they have um an
option to hang out to with, but maybe
maybe if it calls for it, maybe Brett
might be able to bring in somebody.
Maybe there might be someone else that
could be able to facilitate. Maybe
someone is a traveling therapist. I
don't know what these things are going
to look like, but I think it's important
to to realize um that there is a lot of
time for conversation, but we also need
to make sure to remember like what are
the metrics that we need to hit as far
as is it safe a safe environment? Is a
person going to feel, you know, are we
having enough frameworks that they're
going to be able to have um what they
need, right? Their environment. I come
from a monastery background training
where you don't control the child, you
control the environment. You provide a
safe space for them to be able to allow
for their journey through the space. And
I feel like that's kind of similar to
what we're hoping to be able to create
with the regulations in some way. What
is that environment and that framework
going to look like so that the person
has a personal relationship with the
medicine that they feel that they are
safe enough to move through it. And also
that in some ways the access was taken
away from that that was taken away from
us from all of us really.
um something that was provided for
thousands of years. And since mushrooms
and fungi have been with us even longer,
they're older than us.
They're older than humanity. They're
older than a lot of the living creatures
that are here. That is
millions and billions of years of
knowledge
that is being able to be provided to us
that because of our own fear of what
that knowledge is, we decided to put a
stop on it. And now we have an
opportunity to lift that stopper and to
honor that actual ancient wisdom that
has been held since the beginning of
time.
Right? So
in some ways we have to carefully undo
our own undoing.
And that's where I feel like this is an
opportunity that we have here to do
that. If we come together and have these
conversations, what are our fears? what
of our concerns so that we can um move
us all collectively towards healing.
Another soap box. Sorry. All right. in.
>> Did you have something?
>> I just wanted to say that um from my
current understanding, we have to create
the standards for lensure for approved
settings. So, someone's home wouldn't be
able to necessarily go through that
lensure process. The only real exception
is probably going to be hospice care for
the time being.
Tellahalth for preparation sessions on
the other hand um that I think is still
universally agreed on. Um, we would have
to have a vote on it. But
yeah, if we can prepare a document for
that, that would and then vote on it,
that would probably be widely supported.
But let's see what happens in the other
meeting.
>> Yeah. No, I agree. I think that as far
as I'm concerned, this is a good
starting point about, you know, this is
this is what was talked about the first
meeting. Go to the second meeting and at
least have this proposed. Okay, this is
the the document that we're hoping to
start from. Um, for the for the sake of
purposes, please don't kill the
messenger. Copy pasting what we can from
this and then being that being, you
know, uh, New Mexico psilocybin um,
advisory, tele medicine, etc. or
something to that effect. But with these
pieces strucken out, um, and then also
having people have a chance to look at
that for sure. um and then kind of
moving it forward as a starting place,
right? You know, we need to kind of keep
things um progressing. And that doesn't
mean that there isn't going to be room
for more discussion or hey wait, I
looked at the document again. This is
kind of something that was concerning to
me. Not to say that that isn't possible
or you know that but this is just a
place to start. This is what we're going
to look at. we can start putting the
pieces of our house together so that we
can actually have a place to live by the
end of the year would be kind of nice.
Um,
and yeah, so I think to your point in as
far as like the settings for the
journeys, I think what I heard you say
Dominic earlier though was something
when you were talking to
uh Brett was the designated areas. still
um Brett was concerned about um a more
flexible
designated area that was different from
Oregon
>> and that sounds a little contradictory
to what in is saying but I'm not sure
where that actually is.
>> No. So the issue in Oregon is that the
locations have to be only psilocybin. So
they can't utilize them for other
purposes and uh and that's Oregon has
had and they're actually trying to
change change that and and definitely
kudos to them for trying to change it.
But what that has meant is it's meant
that a lot of clinics and areas could
not be offering other services in those
same spaces. And so it really restricted
them. And what we're saying is for
example, and Katherine, I'm just going
to use you since you're here. If
Katherine for example is doing other
types of therapy in that space, whether
it be MDMA, uh, you know, or any other
type of therapy, it still can also be
utilized then for psilocybin, whereas
that is not the case um, currently in
Oregon. Again, hopefully that will
change, but uh, and that's where that
flexibility comes in. But as a reminder,
this program as the statute is set up is
it is a medical program. And so there
does have to be that sort of that
medical supervision for the medical
services aspects of it. And so that's
something to remember to keep in mind.
What exactly that medical um that
medical supervision requires as far as
like lensure that's a part of what still
needs to be determined.
And then also to that point, I know that
maybe this is getting a little bit well
it's not let's just say this is um
cultural considerations and it still
works but um to your point in as far as
like the hospice setting and not in a
house someone else's house um
opinion on whether or not it should be
in someone's house aside. Um, but to
Catherine's point about, you know, where
would the setting be if someone wanted
it to be outside so forth? Now, putting
a pin in both of those things from my
understanding um what the uh
what uh Larry and Janice and them are
doing as far as creating the clinical
trials and figuring out what would be
the best way to conduct the trials is
that and that's also somewhat different
because I'm hearing that's trials and
not actually establishing facilitation
of it after the fact.
outdoor use in the woods. That's what I
hear a lot of people wanting to do. So
that is in some ways contradictory to
what we have proposed now as far as like
hospice settings or
is there room for us to be able to have
you know both or is that what that's the
whole purpose of like we need to have
that flexibility of if it's attached to
if the outdoor setting is attached to a
specific facility.
Does that make sense or am I completely
like going all over the place?
>> No, it makes sense, Desba. Um, part of
what it is is some of those requirements
need to be determined. Um, and it was
brought up in the chat. I'm not sure who
said it a little earlier, but uh, safety
concerns and considerations. for
example, uh you're not going to want to
do a do this in a setting where somebody
could potentially wander off and hurt
themselves simply by falling into an
aoyo or something else. And so when
we're talking about approved settings,
some of those requirements need to be
set up, but it's going to need to ensure
the safety of practitioners,
participants, patients, you know,
everybody who's involved in being able
to do that. Are there some potential
pathways
perhaps? But what one of the things that
we have actually had and the idea that
Ian has brought up is something that we
had considered from a programmatic
standpoint with regard to hospice in
specific because you can't expect
somebody who is in hospice to then
travel 10 miles or even a mile down the
road. Um, so we need to do we do need to
figure some of those aspects out and
part of that is going to also be what
will be acceptable legally, you know,
and sometimes we're going to have to
make compromises. But these are good
questions. These are good things to be
considering. It's exactly what we need
to be discussing and talking about. The
thing to remember is within the
strictctures of the statute. Um because
there are a lot of people who have
brought up other aspects in other
conversations and meetings that just are
not within the realm of the statute. For
example, decriminalization.
This is not a statute about
decriminalization. It is about medical
use. We have to focus on that aspect.
And that's not about anybody's in
particular personal thoughts or beliefs.
It's just we have a particular um you
know a particular um um set of
instructions that are outlined within
the statute and we have to follow those.
Um and then I just because there's not a
lot of time left in the meeting and I do
have somebody did make a comment about
would insurance requirements have an
impact on the discussion. Um, so just
with regard to that is insurance may
always have their own requirements. Um,
and they may be different or more strict
than what is allowed by the program. It
doesn't mean the program wouldn't
necessarily allow it, but it may mean
that some individuals uh in order to get
reimbursement or providers in order to
get reimbursement through insurance or
even Medicaid may have to meet more
strict requirements. Um, so that is a a
different uh aspect of it, but it's a
great question. And so that's something
to remember as well. From a program
standpoint, we may have a lot of
flexibility within the regulations, but
insurance may require some other uh have
may have other more strict requirements
and they do that in other therapies and
other medical procedures as well. So
that's something to remember. But um
Brenda had her hand up and I just want
to make sure that we don't miss out on
Brenda being able to speak just and I
only say that because we have 10 minutes
left in the meeting. So if that's okay,
I'm gonna I'm gonna shut up now and let
Brenda go. Go ahead Brenda. You should
be unmuted.
>> One really quick point. It's just very
quick. The reason for tellaalth uh and
is because it fails. You could be in the
middle of something with someone and it
completely goes out and that's why it
should be done in person the you know
the the primary treatment or um healing
process because I can tell you that I'd
have to call somebody on the phone and
sometimes their phone is out or it's not
charged. So there's a lot of technical
difficulties that happen with teleaalth.
So during the preliminary um uh
counseling
um but during the uh psilocybin session
yes all must be present.
>> Thank you Brenda. I think just for the
sake not that this is official but just
for the sake of understanding can anyone
raise physic uh if you can use the um
emoji raise hand. Uh I just wanted to
get a vote of how many people are
um
it's a two-part
you know with the idea of like tella
health you know that this is um
evaluations are good journeys not so
much
but at least understanding that the kind
of to what Katherine was saying
evaluations integration that's how she's
using it as the tellahalth as like a a
sandwiching
that the journey itself needs to be
one-on-one and that's like the only
thing we can have conversations it's for
another time but um does anybody have
like yes journeys need to be one-on-one
um in that particular place but
essentially tellah health is important
for
we have like people raising hands in the
emojis
can we see can we see those
>> uh we and in the participants on that
side but I I think uh there's just a a
question about clarification are we we
asking tea health appropriate for the um
uh the integration aspects both pre and
post
>> yeah pre and post at the very least
evaluation I know that that's just it's
just mostly it's like I what I'm hearing
is we need to be careful about saying
tellaalth for journeys and journeys
means administering and facilitating
one-on-one medicine with the people. Um,
that's that's a core of what we need.
>> I heard earlier and I agree with um that
not the integration as well. So
preparation, all the screening,
>> cool tellahalth.
>> Um,
>> okay.
>> The administration session and the
therapy or integration, whatever that
ends up being, um, not cool. Okay.
>> Can we have a vote on that?
>> Yeah. Evaluation only. Not to say that
it couldn't possibly in include the
integration, let's just say. But just at
the very least, the very least tellaalth
evaluation
um is important,
right? and that um integration not sorry
tellaalth is important and that the
facilitation
should be at the very least one-on-one
got four five okay
and I know that's really hard so that's
fine if you know you still need time to
think about it because there's you know
especially for people who are not quite
versed in what this looks like it might
be a little bit hard but I just kind of
wanted to
Based on visually
tella health
is
tellahalth for evaluation
journeys facilitation should be
oneonone. All right.
A
>> and just to clarify, this is not a
requirement that those therapy aspects
be telealth. It's just that it is an
option, not a requirement.
>> There are many people who prefer in
person.
>> Yeah. No. Yeah. It that's al also
another thing. Language is very
important. We need to kind of get I just
kind of wanted to see where people were
at as far as and we're not voting really
like it's not like an official vote. I
just wanted to see where people were at.
I want everyone to contact the email
with any other concerns and suggestions.
I know some people don't like speaking
out loud um but are better about
writing. That's great. Sending this
information for other people. My
suggestion is subject line with the
committee meeting that you were at the
date. um maybe just a little blurb um
tellaalth or something just that way it
will really help to kind of pinpoint
what the subject is that you want to
talk about or the concern or the
question which is um I think will help
with with just understanding where we're
all at. Thank you so much for this.
Again, there's going to be another
meeting um on Wednesday the 7th from
5:30 to 6:30. So, if you wanted to
continue to have a conversation and or
tell other people who weren't able to
come today, know it's the holidays. Um,
I do appreciate all of the opinions and
concerns that we all have throughout.
Thank you for taking the time and your
patience with me and with everyone as
we're figuring out what we need to do to
move forward with our um the board and
our committees. Um, if there are other
concerns, like I said, just I really
want us all to be able to formulate what
we need to talk about. And even if we
don't get into the weeds just today, you
know, making sure that we have that,
this is very, very important to me. All
of your concerns are very, very
important. We need to hear them all. So,
thank you so much. I appreciate it.
I don't know if there's any other
things, but you're free to go.
Thank you to everybody
and happy new year.
>> Happy new year.
>> Thank you Desba. Uh I will now be ending
the event.
>> Thank you.